Bayless family papers, 1851-1952 (bulk 1880-1910)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Bayless family papers, 1851-1952 (bulk 1880-1910)
AZ 228
Bayless family
This collection includes correspondence, legal papers, financial records, land patents, and account books of William Henry Bayless and his sons relating to cattle and sheep ranching operations in Kansas, Nebraska, South Dakota, and Arizona. Also includes letters written to J.F. Shields during the Civil War, poetry written by Shields during the war, and later letters to his daughter from her husband, John Bayless. Personal materials consist of photographs and personal papers, including estate documents.
3.3 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
The Bayless family were pioneers in Arizona. William H. Bayless and his sons, Charles and John, were involved in cattle and sheep ranching in Kansas, Nebraska and South Dakota before coming to Arizona in 1883. With Jehiel W. Berkalew, they established Bayless and Berkalew to manage land holdings and ranching operations in southern Arizona. J. F. Shields was a Civil War officer with the 13th Kansas Volunteers. His daughter, Elizabeth, married John Bayless.
Organization
This collection is organized into six series:
Series I: Personal Material, 1890-1952
Series II: Business Correspondence and Papers, 1870-1923
Series III: Shields family Material, 1862-1926
Series IV: Bayless family Letter Books, 1899-1919
Series V: Tax and Legal Papers, 1870-1923
Series VI: Business, Financial and Livestock Records, 1851- 1931
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes correspondence, legal papers, financial records, land patents, and account books of William Henry Bayless and his sons relating to cattle and sheep ranching operations in Kansas, Nebraska, South Dakota, and Arizona. Also includes letters written to J.F. Shields during the Civil War, poetry written by Shields during the war, and later letters to his daughter from her husband, John Bayless. Personal materials consist of photographs and personal papers, including estate documents.
Bayless, William Henry, 1829-1926; Bayless, Charles Henry, 1863-1938; Bayless, John Stuart; Berkalew, Jehiel W.; Shields, John F., d. 1909; Bayless family -- Archives; Bayless and Berkalew Company -- Records and correspondence; Cattle trade -- West (U. S.) -- History -- Sources; Cattle trade -- Arizona -- History -- Sources; Sheep industry -- Arizona -- History -- Sources; Land titles -- Arizona; Carlink Ranch (Ariz.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources; Correspondence; Account books; Photographs
Container List
- Series I: Personal Material, 1890-1952
  - Miscellaneous personal material including photographs. 1890-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Business Correspondence and Papers, 1870-1923
  - Correspondence. 1870-1920 (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
  - Miscellaneous livestock papers including sales, inventories, pedigree receipts, shipping bills, etc. 1872-1902, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series III: Shields family Material, 1862-1926
  - J. F. Shields: Correspondence from family and friends. 1862-1871 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - J. F. Shields: Correspondence with his fiance, Ludie. 1867, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - J. F. Shields and family: Miscellaneous materials including photographs, a diary and correspondence. 1886-1887, 1902-1903 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - J. F. Shields: Poetry including original poetry written during the Civil War. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - J. F. Shields: Scrapbook. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - John S. Bayless and Elizabeth Shields Bayless material. 1897-1903, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Bayless family Letter Books, 1899-1919
  - Letter Book. 1899-1906, 1914-1919 (Box 3)
  - Letter Book. 1905-1909 (Box 3)
- Series V: Tax and Legal Papers, 1870-1923
  - Territorial and Cochise County taxes. 1894, 1902-1905 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Territorial and Graham County taxes. 1902 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Territorial, State and Pinal County taxes. 1885-1918 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Territorial, State and Pima County taxes. 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - State, Pima County and City taxes. 1918-1923 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Tucson city taxes. 1906-1907 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - U. S. Land Patents. 1885, 1889-1893, 1895, 1898-1899, 1904, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Legal papers: Kansas. 1870-1896 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Legal papers: Arizona land and real estate. 1885-1899 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Legal papers: Arizona land and real estate. 1900-1922 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Legal papers: Arizona livestock. 1884-1901, 1906-1907, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Legal papers: Arizona water rights. 1880-1902 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Legal papers: Miscellaneous. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Series VI: Business, Financial and Livestock Records, 1851- 1931
  - Financial Statements: Kansas and Nebraska. 1892-1897 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Bills and Receipts: Kansas and Nebraska. 1877-1878, 1882-1897 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Bills and Receipts: Kansas, books and subscriptions. 1889-1897 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Financial Statements: Arizona. 1884-1894, 1903-1905, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Bills and Receipts: Arizona. 1883-1898, 1900-1909, 1913-1918 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Bills and Receipts: Personal, miscellaneous. 1877-1884, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Ledger. 1851-1897 (Box 6)
  - Ledger. 1892-1898 (Box 6)
  - Ledger. 1895-1896 (Box 6)
  - Ledger. 1917-1931 (Box 6)
  - Cash Book. September 1889-September 1892 (Box 6)
  - Cash Book. September 1892-July 1899 (Box 6)
  - Cash Book. September 1899-1901 (Box 6)
  - Cash Book. 1899-1901 (Box 6)
  - Cash Book "Oracle, Arizona." 1895-1897 (Box 6)
  - Cash Book "Oracle, Arizona." 1897-1901 (Box 6)
  - Account Book: Journal. 1887-1897 (Box 7)
  - Account Book: Ledger. 1884-1885 (Box 7)
  - Account Book: Day book. 1887-1888 (Box 7)
  - Account Book: Livestock records. 1893-1899 (Box 7)
  - Account Book. 1879-1880, 1890-1897 (Box 7)
  - Account Book. 1887-1893 (Box 7)
  - Account Book: Accounts. 1890-1891 (Box 7)
  - Account Book: Cattle records. 1896-1898 (Box 7)
  - Account Book: Miscellaneous accounts. 1892-1897 (Box 7)
  - Account Book and Mexico cattle records. 1884-1885 (Box 7)
  - Account Book: Accounts. 1886-1894 (Box 7)
  - Account Book: Livestock records. 1885-1886, 1901-1906 (Box 7)
  - Account Book: "Provisions from Oracle." January 1897 (Box 7)
  - Accounts and shearing records. 1904-1906 (Box 7)
  - Lumber Book for Store. 1885 (Box 7)
  - W. H. Bayless Pass Books (2). No Dates (Box 7)
  - W. H. Bayless Pass Book. ca. 1855 (Box 7)
  - Journal. 1897-1904 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous bank records including promissory notes, deposit slips, etc. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Bank Statements. 1896-1901, 1903, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Checks. 1898-1905 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Book of check stubs (3). 1896-1907 (Box 8)